<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R | Peter Lugtig</title>
    <link>https://peterlugtig.com/tags/r/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://peterlugtig.com/tags/r/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>R</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2019 - 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2015 13:51:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>R</title>
      <link>https://peterlugtig.com/tags/r/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Which devices do respondents use over the course of a panel study?</title>
      <link>https://peterlugtig.com/post/what-devices-do-respondents-use-over/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2014 15:44:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterlugtig.com/post/what-devices-do-respondents-use-over/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uu.nl/staff/VToepoel&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Vera Toepoel&lt;/a&gt;
 and I have been writing a few articles over the last two years about how survey respondents are taking up tablet computers and smartphones. We were interested in studying whether people in a probability-based web panel (
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lissdata.nl/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;the LISS panel&lt;/a&gt;
) use different devices over time, and whether siwtches in devices for completing surveys are associated with more or less measurement error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to answer this question, we have coded the User Agent Strings of the devices used by more than 6.000 respondents over a six month period. (see the publication tab for a syntax on how to do this using R).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We find, as others have done, that in every wave about 10% of respondents either use a tablet or smartphone. What is new in our analyses is that we focus on the question whether respondents persistently use the same device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The table below shows that PC users largely stick to their PC in all waves. For example, we see that 77.4% of PC-respondents in April, again use a PC in May. Only 1.5% of April’s PC respondents switch to either a tablet or smartphone to complete a questionnaire in May.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Table.&lt;/strong&gt; Devices used between April and September 2013 by LISS panel respondents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-GBK0uZ9jCuQ/VH3RelGgypI/AAAAAAAACsg/lKOeVcgPHb0/s1600/lugtig%2Band%2Btoepoel%2Btable%2B1.png&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-GBK0uZ9jCuQ/VH3RelGgypI/AAAAAAAACsg/lKOeVcgPHb0/s1600/lugtig%2Band%2Btoepoel%2Btable%2B1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;N = 6,226. Click to enlarge&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proportion of respondents switching a PC for either a tablet or smartphone is similarly low in the other months, and is never more than 5%. This stability in device use for PCs is, however, not found for tablets and smartphones. Once people are using a smartphone in particular, they are not very likely to use a smartphone in the next waves of LISS. Only 29 per cent of smartphone users in July 2013, again uses a smartphone in August for example. The consistency of tablet usage increases over the course of the panel; 24% of respondent is a consistent tablet user in April-May, but this increases to 64% in July-August.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, it is worth to note that the use of either a smartphone or a tablet is more likely to lead to non-participation in the next wave of the survey. This may however be a sample selection effect. More loyal panel members may favor the PC to complete the questionnaires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More in a next post on the differences between respondents answer behavior over time, when they switch devices. Do respondents become worse when they answer a survey on a smartphone or tablet?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can download the full paper 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/ew6rtantczkpi7y/Lugtig%20and%20Toepoel%20%28prepublication%29.pdf?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Longitudinal interview outcome data reduction: Latent Class and Sequence analyses</title>
      <link>https://peterlugtig.com/post/longitudinal-interview-outcome-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2013 16:22:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterlugtig.com/post/longitudinal-interview-outcome-data/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Frauke Kreuter once commented on a presentation I gave that I should really be looking at sequence analysis for studying attrition in panel surveys. She had written an article on the topic with Ulrich Kohler (
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jos.nu/Articles/abstract.asp?article=252203&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
) in 2009, and as of late there are more people exploring the technique (e.g. Mark Hanly at Bristol, and 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.southampton.ac.uk/demography/about/staff/gbd.page&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Gabi Durrant at Southampton&lt;/a&gt;
).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am working on a project on attrition in the British Household Panel, and linking attrition errors to measurement errors. Attrition data can be messy. Below, you see the response outcome sequences of every initial panel member in the British Household Panel Survey. This figure obscures the fact individual respondents may frequently switch states (e.g. interview - noncontact - interview - refusal - not issued).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-JQnC4Q1FXFw/Une6AMXsrHI/AAAAAAAACn0/sfGgWexzVlA/s1600/Plot&amp;#43;all&amp;#43;sequences&amp;#43;BHPS.png&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-JQnC4Q1FXFw/Une6AMXsrHI/AAAAAAAACn0/sfGgWexzVlA/s400/Plot+all+sequences+BHPS.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Figure 1:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;relative sizes of final interview outcomes at 18 waves of BHPS of wave 1 respondents&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although descriptive visualizations like these are informative, sequence analysis becomes analytically interesting when you try to &amp;ldquo;do&amp;rdquo; something with the sequences of information. In my case, I want to group all sequence chains into &amp;ldquo;clusters&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;classes&amp;rdquo; of people who have a similar process of attrition. 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stata-journal.com/article.html?article=st0111&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stata&lt;/a&gt;
 and 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://mephisto.unige.ch/traminer/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;R TraMineR&lt;/a&gt;
 offer possibilities for doing this. Both packages enable you to match sequences by 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Optimal_matching&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;optimal matching&lt;/a&gt;
, so that for every sequence from every person you get a distance measure to every other sequence (person). In turn, this (huge) dustance matrix can then be used to classify all the sequences of all respondents into clusters. R offers a nice way to handle huge data matrices, by using aggregation and weighting by the way. See the 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://mephisto.unige.ch/weightedcluster/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;WeightedCluster&lt;/a&gt;
 library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below, you find the results of the sequence analysis. The nice thing is that I end up with 6 clusters that look the same as the Classes that I got out of a Latent Class Analysis over summer. So now I feel much more confident using this classification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-5-Z64s2GcV4/Une6APMFHsI/AAAAAAAACoA/JQ-QJeO7S0A/s1600/6-cluster&amp;#43;solution&amp;#43;from&amp;#43;sequence&amp;#43;analysis&amp;#43;on&amp;#43;BHPS&amp;#43;attrition&amp;#43;data.png&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-5-Z64s2GcV4/Une6APMFHsI/AAAAAAAACoA/JQ-QJeO7S0A/s640/6-cluster+solution+from+sequence+analysis+on+BHPS+attrition+data.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Figure 2: 6-cluster solution for sequence analysis on BHPS attrition patterns&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The differences between sequence analysis and LCA are really minimal, and probably result from the fact that the Optimal Matching algorithm used in sequence analysis is more flexible (in that it would allow deletion, additions, substitutions etc to match), than Latent Class Analysis. But in practice, for my analyses, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter what technique I use. My results are equivalent. Personally, I like Latent Class analysis more, because it offers the option of linking the Latent Classes of attrition to substantive research data in one model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Attrition data bear a resemblence to contact data recorded in a telephone or face-to-face survey. Interviewers make call or interview attempts, that bear a lot of information about the survey proecess, and could improve fieldwork, and reduce nonresponse and costs. I am imagining a paper where one links contact data at every wave, and combines that with attrition analyses, in a series of linked-sequence data analysis. That way, you can learn how specific sequences of call and contact data, lead to specific sequences of interview outcomes at later stages of the panel survey. It can be done if you have a lot of time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SEM software</title>
      <link>https://peterlugtig.com/post/sem-software/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Oct 2011 11:55:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterlugtig.com/post/sem-software/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not dead! In fact, I have been very alive over the past half a year: moving, finishing my Ph.D and starting a new job. With all that settled, I am determined to start where I left off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I often get questions about software to do Structural Equation Modeling. There are quite a few packages out there, some more user-friendly or sophisticated than others. Here is an overview of existing packages and my opinion on the pro&amp;rsquo;s and cons of each.&lt;br&gt;

&lt;a href=&#34;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-VbHwXVzP5cM/Tp6fdypvVFI/AAAAAAAACdI/cdqarK5Rmw4/s1600/meetmodel&amp;#43;3&amp;#43;indicatoren.bmp&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-VbHwXVzP5cM/Tp6fdypvVFI/AAAAAAAACdI/cdqarK5Rmw4/s200/meetmodel+3+indicatoren.bmp&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&amp;lsquo;Old&amp;rsquo; software:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
I was trained to work with LISREL as a student. 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ssicentral.com/lisrel/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;LISREL&lt;/a&gt;
 still exists, but updates have become sparse over the last decade. It was developed by 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karl_Gustav_J%C3%B6reskog&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Karl Joreskog&lt;/a&gt;
, one of the great pioneers of SEM and 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.linkedin.com/pub/dag-s%C3%B6rbom/17/572/85b&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dag Sorbom&lt;/a&gt;
. Although it hasn&amp;rsquo;t been updated for over 5 years, it is still one of the most widely used software packages. The great thing about LISREL is that it allows flexibility. It can handle categorical data and multilevel-data. The LISREL language has been adopted by other SEM-packages. LISREL requires users to know some matrix algebra, to understand what specific parameters to estimate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vcu.edu/mx/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mx&lt;/a&gt;
 and 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mvsoft.com/products.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;EQS&lt;/a&gt;
 were until the end of the 1990s the main competitors to LISREL. Mx has been revamped as an R-package (
&lt;a href=&#34;http://openmx.psyc.virginia.edu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;openMx&lt;/a&gt;
), while EQS is still in use today. I have never worked with EQS myself, but because of the involvement of 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://gseis.ucla.edu/people/bentler&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Peter Bentler&lt;/a&gt;
 in the EQS-project, it has always been cutting-edge when it comes to the handling of categorical data. There seem to be few people using the software, and although being updated now and then, the possibilities in EQS when it comes to mixture and multilevel-models seem limited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www-01.ibm.com/software/analytics/spss/products/statistics/amos/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;AMOS&lt;/a&gt;
 is still one of my favorites, although since taken over by the evil empire of  SPSS, development has grinded to a standstill. The thing I love about AMOS is its drag-and-drop interface, and is user-friendliness. I use AMOS to teach students the first things about SEM, and it works great. AMOS has no possibility to handle multi-level data or mixture models however, and although it can deal with categorical data, there are other packages that do a better job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;lsquo;New&amp;rsquo; software:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Since 2000 some new software packages have taken over the role of LISREL, Mx and EQS as leading software packages. They are either more user-friendly, are better integrated with standard statistical software, or more sophisticated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.statmodel.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;MPLUS&lt;/a&gt;
 is currently the package to beat. It is an extremely sophisticated programme, with frequent large updates. When it comes to modeling possibilities, there is no other package that comes close to MPLUS. It can handle all types of mixture models, and now includes a Bayesian module that opens a whole new world for statistical modelers. 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://pages.gseis.ucla.edu/faculty/muthen/biography.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Bengt Muthen&lt;/a&gt;
 is the driving force behind Mplus, contributing greatly to the expansion of SEM models beyond psychometrics and sociometrics. I work with Mplus on a daily basis, and together with some colleagues at Utrecht University, we regularly organize meetings, or teach courses in Mplus. See 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fss.uu.nl/mplus&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;www.fss.uu.nl/mplus&lt;/a&gt;
 if you want to know more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stata (
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gllamm.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Glamm&lt;/a&gt;
) and Sas (
&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SAS_%28software%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;procalis&lt;/a&gt;
) have integrated SEM packages into their main statistical packages. I have never worked with these packages before, but from the literature it seems they are capable of doing the basic SEM analysis (factor models, path models) in a good way. Procalis has a good module for doing Latent Class and Latent transition analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://statisticalinnovations.com/products/latentgold.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Latent Gold&lt;/a&gt;
 is another package especially designed for Latent Class analysis and mixture models, although it can handle simpler types of SEM as well. The power of this software package lies in the flexibility of specifying link functions between observed and latent variables. It is currently the only package that can deal with ordinal latent variables and boasts some intelligent algorithms that make the estimation of mixture models way faster than for example Mplus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, three packages in 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/R_%28programming_language%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt;
 can do SEM. The great benefit of these packages is that they are open source, and allow the user to program functions himself, or to integrate R-scripts with packages prorgrammed by others. 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://openmx.psyc.virginia.edu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;OpenMx&lt;/a&gt;
 (mentioned earlier) and 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://lavaan.ugent.be/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Lavaan&lt;/a&gt;
 seem to the two packages that are currently most advanced. I&amp;rsquo;ve heard mixed opinions about the 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://socserv.mcmaster.ca/jfox/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;sem&lt;/a&gt;
 package in R, so would not opt for that package&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
