<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>nonresponse | Peter Lugtig</title>
    <link>https://peterlugtig.github.io/tags/nonresponse/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://peterlugtig.github.io/tags/nonresponse/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>nonresponse</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2019 - 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Jun 2018 11:16:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>nonresponse</title>
      <link>https://peterlugtig.github.io/tags/nonresponse/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mobile-only web survey respondents</title>
      <link>https://peterlugtig.github.io/post/mobile-only-web-survey-respondents/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2017 19:52:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterlugtig.github.io/post/mobile-only-web-survey-respondents/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My breaks between posts are getting longer and longer. Sorry my dear readers. Today, I am writing about research done over a year ago that I did with 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.uu.nl/staff/VToepoel&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Vera Toepoel&lt;/a&gt;
 and 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/alerk-amin-908394/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Alerk Amin.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our study was about a group of respondents we can no longer ignore: Mobile-only web survey respondents. These are people, who do no longer use a laptop or desktop PC and use their smartphone for most or any of their Internet browsing, but instead use a smartphone. If we as survey methodologists want these people to answer our surveys, we &lt;em&gt;have to&lt;/em&gt; design our surveys for smartphones as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who are these mobile-only web survey respondents? This population may of course differ across countries. We used data from the American Life Panel, run by RAND, to investigate what this group looked like in the United States, using data from 2014 (so the situation today may be a bit different). The full paper can be found 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://surveypractice.scholasticahq.com/article/2803-mobile-only-web-survey-respondents&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We find that of all people participating in 7 surveys conducted in the panel, 7% is mobile-only in practice. This is not a huge proportion, but it may matter a lot if these 7% of respondents are very different from other types of respondents. We find that they are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to study how different these respondents are, we define 5 groups based on the device the use for responding to surveys:&lt;br&gt;
1. Respondents who always use a PC for completing surveys. This the largest group (68%) and therefore serves as the reference group)&lt;br&gt;
2. Respondents who always use a tablet (5%)&lt;br&gt;
3. Respondents who always use a smartphone ( 7% - our group of interest)&lt;br&gt;
4. Respondents who mix tablets and Pcs (7%)&lt;br&gt;
5. Respondents who mix phones and Pcs (10%)&lt;br&gt;
A further 1% uses all devices, but we ignore these respondents here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://2.bp.blogspot.com/-tsKhJYMzMnQ/WQIezJ94h6I/AAAAAAAAC6c/DqazrgtOwMkPZjqYfnvo2By_Rhay2tPFwCLcB/s1600/plot%2Bmarginal%2Beffcets.png&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://2.bp.blogspot.com/-tsKhJYMzMnQ/WQIezJ94h6I/AAAAAAAAC6c/DqazrgtOwMkPZjqYfnvo2By_Rhay2tPFwCLcB/s400/plot%2Bmarginal%2Beffcets.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click Figure to enlarge. The effects shown are always in comparison to the reference group, which is the ‘always PC’ group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 5 groups serve as our dependent variable in a multinomial logit regression. The average marginal effects shown in the Figure above respresent the change in the likelihood of being in the &amp;lsquo;always PC&amp;rsquo; group as compared to one of the other groups. The negative age coefficient of -.03 for the always phone group means that with every decade respondents get younger (a negative effect), they have a .03 higher probability to be be in the always phone group as referred to the always Pc group. These effects seem small, but they are not. An imaginary respondent aged 60 has a predicted probability of 92 percent of being in the always PC group as opposed to the always phone group, but this probability is about 80 percent for someone aged 20, controlling for the effects of other covariates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our take-away? Apart from age, &amp;lsquo;Always phone’ respondents are also less likely to have a higher education (Bachelor degree or higher), are more likely to be married, and more likely to be of Hispanic or African American ethnicity. These characteristics coincide with some of the most important characteristics of hard-to-recruit respondents. While designing your surveys for smartphones will not get these hard-to-recruit respondents into your panel, you can easily lose them by not designing your surveys for smartphones.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Personality predicts the likelihood and process of attrition in a panel survey</title>
      <link>https://peterlugtig.github.io/post/personality-predicts-likelihood-and/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2014 17:12:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterlugtig.github.io/post/personality-predicts-likelihood-and/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Studies into the correlates of nonresponse often have to rely on socio-demographic variables to study whether respondents and nonrespondents in surveys differ. Often there is no other information available on sampling frames that researchers can use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is unfortunate, for two reasons. First, the  variables we are currently using to predict nonrespons, usually explain a very limited amount of variance of survey nonresponse. Therefore, these variables are also not effective correctors for nonresponse. So, socio-demographic variables are not that interesting to have as sampling frame data. See my earlier posts 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.peterlugtig.com/2013/10/to-weight-or-to-impute-for-unit.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
 and 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.peterlugtig.com/2013/10/imagine-we-have-great-covariates-for.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also unfortunate, because theoretically, we can come up with other respondent characteristics that should explain nonresponse much better. For example, whether respondents believe surveys to be important, whether they enjoy thinking (need for cognition) and whether they have a conscientious personality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I published a new paper today in Sociological Methods and Research, that links these variables in particular to different patterns of attrition in a longitudinal survey. See the full paper 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://smr.sagepub.com/content/early/2014/02/06/0049124113520305.abstract&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the 2007 sample members of the Dutch 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lissdata.nl/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;LISS Panel&lt;/a&gt;
, I tested for different drop out patterns, and classified respondents according to their attrition process. Some respondents are continuous respondents (stayers - on top), while others start enthusiastically, but drop out at various stages of the survey (lines going down), or never really enthusiastically participate (lurkers - erratic lines in the middle).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-n_UBRgc5b2s/UvUBfNfR5XI/AAAAAAAACpY/ayRtFnVLhSo/s1600/LCA&amp;#43;9&amp;#43;SMR.png&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-n_UBRgc5b2s/UvUBfNfR5XI/AAAAAAAACpY/ayRtFnVLhSo/s1600/LCA+9+SMR.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 1: attrition patterns among original LISS sample members (click to enlarge)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a next step, I linked the attrition classes to a set of predictors. Among them socio-demographic variables, but also psychological, and survey related ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 3 strongest predictors of the differences between the attrition patterns (latent classes) are:&lt;br&gt;
- Personality. Conscientious and less extravert people drop out less often&lt;br&gt;
- Survey enjoyment. If people enjoy completing surveys, they are not likely to drop out.&lt;br&gt;
- Having received a PC. The LISS panel gave respondents without Internet access a computer and broadband Internet to enable them to participate. Almost none of the people who received such a computer dropped out from the study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.peterlugtig.com/2012/09/is-panel-attrition-same-as-nonresponse.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;In an earlier post&lt;/a&gt;
 about an upcoming book chapter, I already noted that the correlates of attrition and initial nonresponse are very different in the LISS, so personality may not explain initial nonresponse in other panel surveys or nonresponse in cross-sectional surveys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be very hard to test my hypothesis that personality is a strong predictor of all types of nonresponse. Unless you would do a survey among employees, and have simultaneous access all personality data from tests that every job applicant at that company took. If you sit on top such data and want me to analyse them, do e-mail me.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The trouble with nonresponse studies</title>
      <link>https://peterlugtig.github.io/post/trouble-of-nonresponse-studies/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2011 14:01:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterlugtig.github.io/post/trouble-of-nonresponse-studies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Gerry Nicolaas (of Natcen) has just written a good review on the nonresponse workshop we both attended this year. See 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://natcenblog.blogspot.com/2011/10/challenges-to-current-practice-of.html#comment-form&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://natcenblog.blogspot.com/2011/10/challenges-to-current-practice-of.html#comment-form&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
The Nonresponse Workshops are a great place to meet and discuss with survey researchers in a small setting. The next workshop is to be held early september 2012 at Statistics Canada. See &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nonresponse.org&#34;&gt;www.nonresponse.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
